Available
Available online
online at
at www.sciencedirect.com
www.sciencedirect.com

Available online at www.sciencedirect.com

ScienceDirect

Available online at www.sciencedirect.com
Procedia Computer Science 00 (2018) 000–000
Procedia
Computer
Science
(2018)
000–000
Procedia
Computer
Science
14200
(2018)
339–346

www.elsevier.com/locate/procedia
www.elsevier.com/locate/procedia

Procedia Computer
Science 00
(2018) 000–000
The
on
Computational
Linguistics
(ACLing
The 4th
4th International
International Conference
Conference
on Arabic
Arabic
Computational
Linguistics
(ACLing 2018),
2018),
www.elsevier.com/locate/procedia
November
17-19
2018,
Dubai,
United
Arab
Emirates
November 17-19 2018, Dubai, United Arab Emirates

Automated
Sentence
Boundary
Detection
Modern
Standard
Automated
Sentence
Boundary
Detection in
in
Modern
Standard
The 4th International
Conference
on Arabic Computational
Linguistics
(ACLing
2018),
November
17-19
2018,
Dubai,
United
Arab
Emirates
Arabic
Arabic Transcripts
Transcripts using
using Deep
Deep Neural
Neural Networks
Networks
a,∗ Detection in Modern
aa
b
Automated
Sentence
Boundary
Standard
b,
Carlos-Emiliano
Pontes
,, Fatiha
Sadat
Carlos-Emiliano González-Gallardo
González-Gallardoa,∗,, Elvys
Elvys Linhares
Linhares
Pontes
Fatiha
Sadat
,
a,b,c
a,b,c
Juan-Manuel
Torres-Moreno
Arabic Transcripts
using
Deep Neural Networks
Juan-Manuel
Torres-Moreno
a LIA - Université d’Avignon et des Pays de Vaucluse, 339 chemin des Meinajaries, 84140, Avignon, France
a LIA - Université d’Avignon et des Pays de Vaucluse, 339 chemin des Meinajaries, 84140, Avignon, France
a,∗
a
b Université du Québec a Montréal, C.P. 8888, succ.
Montréal (Québec) H3C 3P8 Canada
b Université du Québec a Montréal, C.P. 8888, succ. Centre-ville,
Centre-ville, Montréal (Québec) H3C 3P8 Canada

Carlos-Emiliano González-Gallardo , Elvys Linhares Pontes , Fatiha Sadatb ,
c GIGL, École Polytechnique de Montréal, C.P. 6079, succ. Centre-ville, Montréal
H3C 3A7 Canada
c GIGL, École Polytechnique de Montréal, C.P. 6079, succ. Centre-ville, Montréal
(Québec) H3C 3A7 Canada
Juan-Manuel Torres-Morenoa,b,c (Québec)
a LIA

Abstract
Abstract

- Université d’Avignon et des Pays de Vaucluse, 339 chemin des Meinajaries, 84140, Avignon, France
du Québec a Montréal, C.P. 8888, succ. Centre-ville, Montréal (Québec) H3C 3P8 Canada
c GIGL, École Polytechnique de Montréal, C.P. 6079, succ. Centre-ville, Montréal (Québec) H3C 3A7 Canada
b Université

The
The increased
increased volumes
volumes of
of Arabic
Arabic sources
sources of
of data
data available
available on
on the
the Web
Web has
has boosted
boosted the
the development
development of
of Natural
Natural Language
Language Processing
Processing
(NLP)
(NLP) tools
tools over
over different
different tasks
tasks and
and applications.
applications. However,
However, to
to take
take advantage
advantage from
from aa vast
vast amount
amount of
of these
these applications,
applications, aa prior
prior
segmentation
Abstract
segmentation task
task call
call Sentence
Sentence Boundary
Boundary Detection
Detection (SBD)
(SBD) is
is needed.
needed. In
In this
this paper
paper we
we focus
focus on
on SBD
SBD over
over Modern
Modern Standard
Standard Arabic
Arabic
(MSA)
(MSA) by
by comparing
comparing two
two different
different approaches
approaches based
based on
on Deep
Deep Neural
Neural Networks
Networks (DNN)
(DNN) using
using out-of-domain
out-of-domain and
and in-domain
in-domain training
training
The
increased
volumes features
of Arabic sources of data
available on the Web has
boosted the development
of Natural Language
Processing
data
data with
with only
only lexical
lexical features (represented
(represented as
as character
character embedding)
embedding) while
while conducting
conducting two
two scenarios
scenarios based
based on
on aa Convolutional
Convolutional
(NLP)
tools overand
different tasks Neural
and applications.with
However, tomechanism
take advantage from a vast
amount ofathese
applications, a prior
Neural
Neural Network
Network and aa Recurrent
Recurrent Neural Network
Network with attention
attention mechanism architectures.
architectures. While
While tuning
tuning a big
big out-of-domain
out-of-domain dataset
dataset
segmentation
task
call Sentence
Boundary
Detection
(SBD) is needed.
In this
paper
we focus
on SBD
over
Modern
Standard
Arabic
with
a
smaller
in-domain
dataset,
improves
the
performance
in
general.
Our
evaluations
were
based
on
IWSLT
with a smaller in-domain dataset, improves the performance in general. Our evaluations were based on IWSLT 2017
2017 TED
TED talks
talks
(MSA)
by comparing
two
different approaches
baseddepending
on Deep Neural
Networks
(DNN)MSA
usingcarries
out-of-domain
and in-domaingiven
training
transcripts
and
showed
similarities
and
differences
of
the
SBD
method.
certain
complications
transcripts and showed similarities and differences depending of the SBD method. MSA carries certain complications given its
its
data
with only lexical
features (represented
as character
embedding)
while conducting
two scenarios
based on the
a Convolutional
rich
rich and
and complex
complex morphology.
morphology. However,
However, using
using only
only lexical
lexical features
features for
for Arabic
Arabic SBD
SBD is
is an
an acceptable
acceptable option
option when
when the source
source audio
audio
Neural
Network
and a Recurrent
Neural Network
with attention mechanism
architectures.
While tuning a big out-of-domain dataset
signal
signal is
is not
not available
available and
and aa certain
certain level
level of
of language
language independence
independence needs
needs to
to be
be reached.
reached.
with a smaller in-domain dataset, improves the performance in general. Our evaluations were based on IWSLT 2017 TED talks
Sentence
Boundary
Detection;
Transcription;
Modern
Neural
Networks
Keywords:
transcripts
showed
similarities
andSpeech-to-Text;
differences
of the
SBDStandard
method.Arabic;
MSADeep
carries
certain
complications given its
©
2018 Theand
Authors.
Published
by Elsevier
B.V. depending
Keywords:
Sentence
Boundary
Detection;
Speech-to-Text;
Transcription;
Modern
Standard
Arabic;
Deep
Neural
Networks
rich
and
complex
morphology.
However,
using
only
lexical
features
for
Arabic
SBD
is
an
acceptable
option
when the source audio
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/)
signal is not under
available
and a certain
level
of language
independence
to be reached.
Peer-review
responsibility
of the
scientific
committee
of the 4thneeds
International
Conference on Arabic Computational Linguistics.
Keywords: Sentence Boundary Detection; Speech-to-Text; Transcription; Modern Standard Arabic; Deep Neural Networks

1.
1. Introduction
Introduction
Arabic
Arabic language
language is
is known
known to
to be
be challenging
challenging given
given its
its complex
complex linguistic
linguistic structure
structure [3]
[3] and
and dialect
dialect variations
variations [14].
[14].
However,
the
development
of
Arabic
Natural
Language
Processing
(NLP)
tools
has
increased
these
last
However,
the development of Arabic Natural Language Processing (NLP) tools has increased these last years,
years, creating
creating
1. Introduction
aa large
large set
set of
of state-of-the-art
state-of-the-art applications
applications including
including POS
POS taggers,
taggers, syntactic
syntactic parsers,
parsers, information
information retrieval,
retrieval, machine
machine
translation,
automatic
speech
recognition
and
synthesis
systems
[9,
17].
Some
NLP
libraries
and
like
translation,
automatic
speech
and given
synthesis
systems linguistic
[9, 17]. Some
NLP [3]
libraries
and tools
tools
like Python
Python
Arabic
language
is known
to recognition
be challenging
its complex
structure
and dialect
variations
[14].
However, the development of Arabic Natural Language Processing (NLP) tools has increased these last years, creating
a ∗large
set of state-of-the-art
applications
author. Tel.: +33 04
90 84 35 68. including POS taggers, syntactic parsers, information retrieval, machine
∗ Corresponding
Corresponding author. Tel.: +33 04 90 84 35 68.
translation,
automatic
speech
recognition
and synthesis systems [9, 17]. Some NLP libraries and tools like Python
E-mail address: carlos-emiliano.gonzalez-gallardo@alumni.univ-avignon.fr
E-mail address: carlos-emiliano.gonzalez-gallardo@alumni.univ-avignon.fr

c 2018 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V.
1877-0509 
c 2018 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V.
1877-0509 
∗ is an open
1877-0509
© 2018
Thearticle
Authors.
Published
by35Elsevier
B.V.
This
access
under
the
CC84
BY-NC-ND
license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/)
author.
Tel.:
+33
04 90
68.
ThisCorresponding
is an open access
article
under
the
CC BY-NC-ND
license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/)
This
is
an
open
access
article under
CC BY-NC-ND
(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/)
Peer-review
under
responsibility
of thethe
scientific
committeelicense
of the 4th
International Conference on Arabic Computational Linguistics.
E-mail
address:
carlos-emiliano.gonzalez-gallardo@alumni.univ-avignon.fr
Peer-review
under
responsibility
of
the
scientific
committee
of theof4th
International
Conference
on ArabiconComputational
Linguistics.Linguistics.
Peer-review under responsibility of the scientific committee
the
4th International
Conference
Arabic Computational
10.1016/j.procs.2018.10.485
c 2018 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V.
1877-0509 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/)
Peer-review under responsibility of the scientific committee of the 4th International Conference on Arabic Computational Linguistics.

340
2

Carlos-Emiliano González-Gallardo et al. / Procedia Computer Science 142 (2018) 339–346
C.E. González-Gallardo et al. / Procedia Computer Science 00 (2018) 000–000

NLTK1 , OpenNLP2 [5], UIMA3 [10], LIMA4 and NooJ5 [26], which were originally created for non Arabic texts now
include Arabic extensions. By contrast, other libraries have been developed exclusively for Arabic.
Althobaiti et al. developed AraNLP [2], which is focused on Arabic preprocessing. This library contains some tools
covering tokenization, stemming, POS tagging, sentence detection, word segmentation, normalization and punctuation/diacritic deletion.
MADAMIRA6 , developed by Pasha et al., is an toolkit which combines two previous Arabic NLP systems:
MADA[13] and AMIRA[7]. It provides the following NLP tools for Modern Standard Arabic (MSA) and the Egyptian
dialect: lemmatization, diacritization, glossing, POS tagging, morphological analysis, morphological disambiguation,
stemming, tokenization, base phrase chunking, name entity recognition and word-level disambiguation [23].
The Software Architecture For Arabic language pRocessing (SAFAR) [27] is a framework developed by Souteh
et al. that aims to gather developed Arabic NLP tools within a single homogeneous architecture and create new
ones if necessary. Implemented tools within SAFAR include morphological analyzers, stemmers, syntactic parsers,
normalizers, tokenizers, sentence splitters, transliteration tools and question answering applications.
Works have also been made regarding unstructured and noisy Arabic texts, found in social media datasets like
microblogs and tweets. Added to the common difficulties of working with structured Arabic texts, Arabic tweets carry
other problems like high degree of ambiguity, spelling mistakes, etc. Mallek et al. [20] implemented a phrase-based
statistical machine translation system from MSA tweets into English. They conclude that a preprocessing step for this
kind of noisy texts is very useful to improve the translation results. El-Masri et al. [8] presented a sentiment analysis
tool over Arabic tweets using a Naive Bayes learning approach. Their model detects the polarity of a group of tweet
classifying it in four possible classes: positive, negative, both and neutral.
Access to Internet multimedia platforms nowadays available like Youtube7 , TED8 and Dailymotion9 opens a new
universe for Arabic NLP tools. Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR) systems can be used to transcribe multimedia
content ASR aims to transform spoken data into a written representation, thus enabling natural human-machine interaction with further NLP tasks [31]. Performance of ASR systems for MSA has improve in the last years given the
amount of data available for training and testing this systems. Tomashenko et al. [28] trained a Deep Neural Network
(DNN) with Gaussian Mixture Models derived features and time-delay neural networks for acoustic models over 1128
hours of MSA broadcast speech and 110 million words, reporting a WER of 23%. Menacer et al. [21] developed an
ASR system for MSA based on the Kaldi toolkit10 [25], where recognition is achieved using a DNN Hidden Markov
model over 63 hours of spoken transcribed data and 1000 million words from the Arabic Gigaword Corpus. They
reported a result of 14.42% in terms of WER.
Despite the good performance of modern ASR systems, transcripts do not carry syntactic information as sentence
boundaries, which is a major problem for further NLP tasks like POS tagging, automatic text summarization [29],
machine translation and sentiment analysis among others. In this paper we address the Sentence Boundary Detection
(SBD) task over MSA transcripts to automatically predict or restore the boundaries over transcripts.
The rest of this article is organized as follows. In Section 2 we present an overview of related work concerning SBD.
The experimental setup is introduced in Section 3. Experiments and results are addressed in Section 4. In Section 5
Discussion over the methods and difficulties are presented. Finally, Section 6 concludes the paper.
1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

https://www.nltk.org/
https://opennlp.apache.org/
https://uima.apache.org/
https://github.com/aymara/lima/wiki
http://www.nooj-association.org/
https://camel.abudhabi.nyu.edu/madamira/
https://www.youtube.com/
https://www.ted.com/
https://www.dailymotion.com/fr
http://kaldi-asr.org/

Carlos-Emiliano González-Gallardo et al. / Procedia Computer Science 142 (2018) 339–346
C.E. González-Gallardo et al. / Procedia Computer Science 00 (2018) 000–000

341
3

2. Sentence Boundary Detection for MSA
Sentence Boundary Detection (SBD) is of vital importance given that in general, ASR systems focus on obtaining the
correct sequence of transcribed words with almost no concern of the overall structure of the document, thus lacking
of syntactic information [12].
A big complication of segmenting a transcript is the flurry definition of sentence in spoken language. In standard
conversations or in simpler scenarios like a monologue, ideas are organized very differently compared to written
language. Added to this, Arabic carries other difficulties like word ambiguity, structural ambiguity, lack of punctuation
marks, use of connective words and agglutination [15].
To our knowledge no much work has been developed over Arabic SBD. The Arabic Texts Segmentation System
or STAr (by its acronym in French), created by Belguith et al. [15] is a text segmentation system for Arabic based
on a set of rules created from the contextual analysis of punctuation marks and a list of particles which play the role
of sentence boundaries. Segmentation consists on the disambiguation of sentence boundaries and paragraphs. Even
though they did not report any experiment with transcripts, while it is possible to apply the method over this type of
data.
Zribi et al. [32] presented three methods for the detection of sentence boundaries in transcribed Tunisian Arabic
using lexical and prosodic features. The first method is composed of two sets of handmade rules: 1) based on oral
specific lexical items and prosodic features and 2) based on connectors, personal and relative pronouns, verbs, etc.
The second method corresponds to a statistical method based on a decision tree algorithm. It classifies a word into
four different classes: 1) first word of a sentence, 2) word within a sentence, 3) last word of a sentence and 4) one
word sentence. The third method combines the previous two in an hybrid framework.

3. Methodology
3.1. Datasets
One of the objectives of the current research is to analyze the impact of cross-domain datasets during the evaluation phase of SBD. The first dataset (TED) corresponds to the Multilingual Task 2017 proposed by The International
Workshop on Spoken Language Translation (IWSLT)11 . It consists of 122 TED talks12 manually transcribed containing 168,354 words. The second dataset (GW) is the Arabic Gigaword13 , which gathers a series of different Arabic
news wires containing around 938M words (after XML extraction). We used a sample of 70,261,169 words which
corresponds to the Asharq Al-Awsat (aaw arb) news wire.
As for the preprocessing, we applied a normalization and tokenization process over both datasets. During the
normalization phase, all punctuation marks (  ?  !  ,  . : ;) were mapped to a common boundary symbol, which
corresponds to the ”BOUNDARY” class. Based on the experiments performed by Alotaiby et al. [1], where they observed that a big lexicon could be reduced about 24.54%, we used the MADAMIRA toolkit to perform a tokenization
over both datasets to reduce the dimensionality. The following proclitics and enclitics were separated, generating two
or more tokens depending of the amount of clitics within the word:


    
     
  
    
    





         

The final size of the datasets after normalization and tokenization as well as the training, validation and testing
distribution can be observed in Table 1. We opted to omit the validation set for TED given its reduced size.
11
12
13

http://workshop2017.iwslt.org/
https://www.ted.com/talks?language=en
https://catalog.ldc.upenn.edu/LDC2011T11

Carlos-Emiliano González-Gallardo et al. / Procedia Computer Science 142 (2018) 339–346
C.E. González-Gallardo et al. / Procedia Computer Science 00 (2018) 000–000

342
4

It is important to remark the class distribution disparity. Given the nature of the dataset, where sentence boundaries are much less frequent that nonsentence boundaries, the ”BOUNDARY” class oscillates between 6.185% and
9.981% (Table 2). Liu et al. developed a wide study [19] addressing this disparity behavior with techniques like downsampling, oversampling and replication in a Hidden Markov Model framework. They concluded that depending on
the evaluation metric and posterior processing, resampling may or not be useful. Table 1 and 2 show some statistics
on the dataset as well as the classes distributions over these datasets.
Table 1. Size and distribution of datasets.
Dataset

train

valid

test

Total

GW
TED

73,608,328
183,314

21,030,957
—

10,515,477
50,881

105,154,762
1942,378

Table 2. Class distribution in percentage (%) over datasets.
Class

train

GW
valid

test

train

TED
test

BOUNDARY
NO BOUNDARY

6.185
93.815

6.519
93.481

6.663
93.337

9.981
90.019

9.699
90.301

3.2. Character embeddings
Word representation is an important topic to consider specially for morphology rich languages like Arabic. Common
embedding strategies like Word2vec [22] or Glove [24] do not consider the internal structure of words, which is
a limitation for morphology rich languages. FastText14 , proposed by Bojanowski et al. [6], is a word embedding
representation where a vector is associated to each n-gram character; therefore, words are represented as the sum of
their character vectors.
We opted for FastText vectors to represent our datasets and conduct our experiments given its advantages concerning morphology rich languages. We performed a 300 dimension vector induction with the complete GW dataset
obtaining 102,248 vectors.
3.3. The Proposed Methods
We are interested in comparing addressed Arabic SBD with two different Neural Network approaches, CNN and
RNN.
3.3.1. CNN (SBDConv )
For this method we took into consideration the Convolutional Neural Network (CNN) models proposed by GonzálezGallardo et al. [11] for French SBD. CNN are a type of DNN in which certain hidden layers behave like filters that
share their parameters across space. At the last part of the CNN, a set of fully connected layers choose within a set of
possible outputs the most probable one. The input layer of a CNN is represented by a m × n matrix where each cell ci j
may correspond to an image’s pixel in image processing. For our purpose this matrix represents the relation between
a window of m words and their corresponding n dimensional FastText vectors.
The hidden layers inside both CNNs consist of an arrange of convolutional, pooling and fully connected layers
blocks. We consider two convolutional layers, with valid padding and stride value of one. The first layer has a 3-shape
14

https://fasttext.cc/

Carlos-Emiliano González-Gallardo et al. / Procedia Computer Science 142 (2018) 339–346
C.E. González-Gallardo et al. / Procedia Computer Science 00 (2018) 000–000

343
5

kernel and 32 output filters while the second has a 2-shape kernel and 64 output filters. To downsample and centralize
the attention of the CNN in the middle word of the window, a max pooling layer with 2x3-shape kernel and stride
of 1x3 is implemented. The final part of the CNN is formed by 3 fully connected layers with 2048, 4096 and 2048
neurons each and a dropout layer attached to the last layer. RELU activation functions are used to remove linearity of
all convolutional, max pooling and fully connected layers.
3.3.2. LSTM (SBDLS T M )
Inspired by [18, 30], our second model follows a sequence-to-sequence paradigm using the attention mechanism to
verify which words of a sentence c represent a sentence boundary (Figure 1). The words in a sentence c are represented
by their FastText embedding. Then, a first LSTM encodes this sentence [16] and a second LSTM with attention
mechanism generates the sequence of labels that determine the sentence boundary. The attention mechanism decides
which input region to focus in order to generate the next output [4]. LSTM with attention mechanism is composed of
input it , control state ct and memory state mt that are updated at time step t (Equations 2-7).
ct = [wet , ct ]

(1)

it = sigm(W1 xt + W2 ht−1 )

(2)

it = tanh(W3 xt + W4 ht−1 )

(3)

ft = sigm(W5 xt + W6 ht−1 )

(4)

ot = sigm(W7 xt + W8 ht−1 )

(5)

mt = mt−1  ft + it  it

(6)

ht = mt  ot

(7)

where the operator  denotes element-wise multiplication, wet is the FastText embedding of the word at the time step
t, ct is the context vector, the matrices W1 , W2 , ..., W8 and the vector h0 are the parameters of the model, and all the
non-linearities are computed element-wise. The context vector ct at time t is calculated as a sum of all hidden states
of the encoder weight:
T

αt j · hEj
(8)
ct =
j=1

rt j = vTα tanh(Wα ht−1 + Uα hEj )
αt j = softmax(rt j )

(9)
(10)

the probability αt j represents the importance of each hidden state of the encoder hEj in the prediction of the current
state ht .
4. Experiments and Evaluations
We conducted two experimental scenarios for SBD over MSA using the neural models described in Section 3.3. Lexical features for both DNN models correspond to the FastText character embeddings described in Section 3.2. Vectors
of OOV words from the embedding model are generated from the word’s n-grams vectors, eliminating unknown
vectors.
The performance is measured as a binary classification task, where the ”BOUNDARY” (BOUND) class corresponds to the words followed by a punctuation mark, while the ”NO BOUNDARY” (NO BOUND) class corresponds
to those words not followed by a punctuation mark. Given the unbalanced nature of the dataset, a global metric like
Accuracy is likely to be biased by the larger class; thus we also compute Precision, Recall and F1 for each class.

Carlos-Emiliano González-Gallardo et al. / Procedia Computer Science 142 (2018) 339–346
C.E. González-Gallardo et al. / Procedia Computer Science 00 (2018) 000–000

344
6

Fig. 1. The words are represented by the word embedding representations. The attention mechanism improves the decode processing. The output
layer is composed of by 0 or 1.

4.1. Scenario 1
With this first scenario (S1 ) we wanted to observe the impact of applying a SBD model trained with a big dataset
collected from written sources over a spoken source dataset. We first conducted training, validation and test on both
SBDConv and SBDLS T M systems with GW train,valid,test for 3 and 7 epochs respectively. Number of epochs were dynamically decided with GW valid before overfitting. Then, we used TEDtest for evaluating the performance of the trained
models over an out-of-domain dataset.
Results for this scenario are shown in Table 3. The high Accuracy (0.963) of SBDConv over the GigaWord test
dataset (SBDConv(GW) ) may give an erroneous idea of the model performance. This behavior repeats over the rest of the
models. The model is really good predicting the NO BOUND class a F1 of 0.980. It is important to note almost 40%
drop in Recall between both classes, which reflects model’s difficulties to retrieve the corresponding instances of the
BOUND class. In most values, SBDLS T M(GW) show a similar performance than SBDConv(GW) . The difference concerns
the BOUND class Recall (0.327) is 46.57% smaller.
Evaluation of SBDConv over TEDtest (SBDConv(T ED) ) shows a interesting behaviour when compared to SBDConv(GW) .
Difference in Precision for both classes, as well as the NO BOUND class in Recall is very small compared to the
Recall BOUND class, which falls about 23.04%. Concerning SBDLS T M for the same test dataset (SBDConv(T ED) ), the
biggest drop in performance also corresponds to the Recall BOUND class, where the difference between them is about
35.47%.
Table 3. S1 results over GW and TED evaluation datasets.
Model

Accuracy

Precision
NO BOUND
BOUND

Recall
NO BOUND

BOUND

F1
NO BOUND

BOUND

SBDConv(GW)
SBDLS T M(GW)

0.963
0.947

0.972
0.954

0.797
0.729

0.989
0.991

0.612
0.327

0.980
0.972

0.684
0.451

SBDConv(T ED)
SBDLS T M(T ED)

0.934
0.914

0.945
0.921

0.752
0.673

0.983
0.989

0.471
0.211

0.964
0.954

0.579
0.321

4.2. Scenario 2
The objective of the second scenario (S2 ) is to measure the effect of adding a small in-domain spoken dataset over
the models trained on S1 . For this scenario we continued training SBDConv and SBDLS T M systems with TEDtrain .
TED dataset size is very small for NN training strategies to consider the creation of a validation set. For this reason,
GW valid was used during validation phase and epoch control for both systems. The reduced size of TEDtrain lead to a

Carlos-Emiliano González-Gallardo et al. / Procedia Computer Science 142 (2018) 339–346
C.E. González-Gallardo et al. / Procedia Computer Science 00 (2018) 000–000

345
7

fast overfitting behaviour, SBDConv was trained only for one epoch while X for SBDLS T M . Evaluation was performed
over the same dataset of S1 (TEDtest ).
Table 4 shows the results for S2 . As in S1 , accuracy values are very high given the class unbalanced. Concerning
SBDConv(T ED) , Precision and Recall for the NO BOUND class is almost the same with just a small difference of 0.005.
Continue training SBDConv with TEDtrain seems to have a negative impact over the BOUND class Precision (0.687),
which is 8.25% lower than in S1 . However, BOUND class Recall improves 39.1%. SBDLS T M(T ED) show a similar
behavior than SBDConv(T ED) , a slight improvement for the BOUND class Recall is present but a decrease for Pecision
is present.
Table 4. S2 results over TED evaluation dataset.
Model
SBDConv(T ED)
SBDLS T M(T ED)

Accuracy
0.938
0.911

Precision
NO BOUND
BOUND
0.963
0.925

0.687
0.597

Recall
NO BOUND
0.968
0.981

BOUND
0.655
0.264

F1
NO BOUND
0.966
0.952

BOUND
0.671
0.366

5. Discussion
Results for S 1 and S 2 show that unbalanced classes distribution seem to impact SBDConv and SBDLS T M in a similar
degree even both methods follow very different learning techniques. SBDConv focus its attention on analyzing the
words contained in a fixed-sized window, making the boundary prediction independent of the actual position within
the transcript. Neverless, this advantage is also a drawback for potentially long sentences given that the method is not
able to analyze long contexts.
By contrast, the SBDLS T M is characterized by the analysis of a sequence of words to propose the sentence boundary
of this sequence. This approach works best when it analyzes a sequence of words at the beginning of sentences.
However, our approach analyzes word sequences that can start in the middle or at the end of sentences, which reduces
the performance of predicting sentence boundaries. In addition, long and complex sentences are a challenge to code
all the information and to generate a correct sentence boundary for this kind of sentences.
6. Conclusion
In this paper we have studied the impact of using cross-domain datasets during the evaluation phase of two Sentence
Boundary Detection systems over Modern Standard Arabic. The obtained results show that tuning a model that was
originally trained with a big out-of-domain dataset with small in-domain dataset, in general, improves its performance.
Both methods presented a similar behavior when the spoken language evaluation dataset was used. This may lead
to think that spoken MSA maintain the same linguistic structures around SUs than written MSA, but also contains
some constructions that written language does not contain.
Our method based on LSTM showed to be less effective compared to the one based on CNNs. We think that letting
the method to learn from more epochs will help to at least equal the performance.
As future work we will optimize the training parameters of both methods and increment the number of classes to
have the possibility of different boundary types. Also, a hybrid system using bi-LSTM and CNN that will combine
the advantages of each method, is among our future research directions.
Acknowledgements
We would like to acknowledge the support of CHISTERA-AMIS ANR-15-CHR2-0001 for funding this research
through the Access Multilingual Information opinionS (AMIS), (France-Europe) project.

346
8

Carlos-Emiliano González-Gallardo et al. / Procedia Computer Science 142 (2018) 339–346
C.E. González-Gallardo et al. / Procedia Computer Science 00 (2018) 000–000

References
[1] Alotaiby, F., Foda, S., Alkharashi, I., 2010. Clitics in arabic language: a statistical study, in: 24th Pacific Asia Conference on Language,
Information and Computation.
[2] Althobaiti, M., Kruschwitz, U., Poesio, M., 2014. Aranlp: A java-based library for the processing of arabic text, in: LREC.
[3] Attia, M., Somers, H., 2008. Handling Arabic morphological and syntactic ambiguity within the LFG framework with a view to machine
translation. volume 279. University of Manchester Manchester.
[4] Bahdanau, D., Cho, K., Bengio, Y., 2014. Neural machine translation by jointly learning to align and translate. CoRR abs/1409.0473.
[5] Baldridge, J., 2005. The OpenNLP project. http://opennlp.apache.org/.
[6] Bojanowski, P., Grave, E., Joulin, A., Mikolov, T., 2016. Enriching word vectors with subword information. preprint arXiv:1607.04606 .
[7] Diab, M., 2009. Second generation amira tools for arabic processing: Fast and robust tokenization, pos tagging, and base phrase chunking, in:
2nd International Conference on Arabic Language Resources and Tools.
[8] El-Masri, M., Altrabsheh, N., Mansour, H., Ramsay, A., 2017. A web-based tool for arabic sentiment analysis. Procedia Computer Science
117, 38–45.
[9] Farghaly, A., Shaalan, K., 2009. Arabic natural language processing: Challenges and solutions. ACM Transactions on Asian Language
Information Processing (TALIP) 8, 14.
[10] Ferrucci, D., Lally, A., 2004. UIMA: An Architectural Approach to Unstructured Information Processing in the Corporate Research Environment. Natural Language Engineering 10, 327–348. doi:10.1017/S1351324904003523.
[11] González-Gallardo, C.E., Torres-Moreno, J.M., 2018. Sentence Boundary Detection for French with Subword-Level Information Vectors and
Convolutional Neural Networks. preprint arXiv:1802.04559 .
[12] Gotoh, Y., Renals, S., 2000. Sentence boundary detection in broadcast speech transcripts, in: ASR2000-Automatic Speech Recognition:
Challenges for the new Millenium ISCA Tutorial and Research Workshop (ITRW).
[13] Habash, N., Rambow, O., Roth, R., 2009. Mada+ tokan: A toolkit for arabic tokenization, diacritization, morphological disambiguation, pos
tagging, stemming and lemmatization, in: 2nd International Conference on Arabic language resources and tools (MEDAR), Cairo, Egypt, p. 62.
[14] Habash, N.Y., 2010. Introduction to arabic natural language processing. Synthesis Lectures on Human Language Technologies 3, 1–187.
[15] Hadrich, L.B., Baccour, L., Mourad, G., 2005. Star: un système de segmentation de textes arabes basé sur lanalyse contextuelle des signes de
ponctuations et de certaines particules, in: TALN’05.
[16] Hochreiter, S., Schmidhuber, J., 1997. Long short-term memory. Neural Computation 9, 1735–1780.
[17] Jaafar, Y., Bouzoubaa, K., 2018. A survey and comparative study of arabic nlp architectures, in: Intelligent Natural Language Processing:
Trends and Applications. Springer, pp. 585–610.
[18] Linhares Pontes, E., Huet, S., Torres-Moreno, J.M., Linhares, A.C., 2018. Cross-language text summarization using sentence and multisentence compression, in: Silberztein, M., Atigui, F., Kornyshova, E., Métais, E., Meziane, F. (Eds.), Natural Language Processing and Information Systems, Springer International Publishing, Cham. pp. 467–479.
[19] Liu, Y., Chawla, N.V., Harper, M.P., Shriberg, E., Stolcke, A., 2006. A study in machine learning from imbalanced data for sentence boundary
detection in speech. Computer Speech & Language 20, 468–494.
[20] Mallek, F., Le, N.T., Sadat, F., 2018. Automatic machine translation for arabic tweets, in: Intelligent Natural Language Processing: Trends and
Applications. Springer, pp. 101–119.
[21] Menacer, M.A., Mella, O., Fohr, D., Jouvet, D., Langlois, D., Smaili, K., 2017. An enhanced automatic speech recognition system for arabic,
in: Third Arabic Natural Language Processing Workshop, pp. 157–165.
[22] Mikolov, T., Chen, K., Corrado, G., Dean, J., 2013. Efficient estimation of word representations in vector space. preprint arXiv:1301.3781 .
[23] Pasha, A., Al-Badrashiny, M., Diab, M.T., El Kholy, A., Eskander, R., Habash, N., Pooleery, M., Rambow, O., Roth, R., 2014. Madamira: A
fast, comprehensive tool for morphological analysis and disambiguation of arabic., in: LREC, pp. 1094–1101.
[24] Pennington, J., Socher, R., Manning, C., 2014. Glove: Global vectors for word representation, in: Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural
Language Processing (EMNLP), pp. 1532–1543.
[25] Povey, D., Ghoshal, A., Boulianne, G., Burget, L., Glembek, O., Goel, N., Hannemann, M., Motlicek, P., Qian, Y., Schwarz, P., et al., 2011.
The Kaldi speech recognition toolkit, in: IEEE 2011 Workshop on Automatic Speech Recognition and Understanding, IEEE Signal Processing
Society.
[26] Silberztein, M., 2005. Nooj: a linguistic annotation system for corpus processing, in: HLT/EMNLP on Interactive Demonstrations, Association
for Computational Linguistics. pp. 10–11.
[27] Souteh, Y., Bouzoubaa, K., 2011. Safar platform and its morphological layer, in: Eleventh Conference on Language Engineering ESOLEC,
pp. 14–15.
[28] Tomashenko, N., Vythelingum, K., Rousseau, A., Estève, Y., 2016. Lium asr systems for the 2016 multi-genre broadcast arabic challenge, in:
Spoken Language Technology Workshop (SLT), 2016, IEEE. pp. 285–291.
[29] Torres-Moreno, J.M., 2014. Automatic Text Summarization. Wiley and Sons.
[30] Tran, N.T., Luong, V.T., Nguyen, N.L.T., Nghiem, M.Q., 2016. Effective attention-based neural architectures for sentence compression with
bidirectional long short-term memory, in: Seventh Symposium on Information and Communication Technology, ACM, New York, NY, USA.
pp. 123–130. URL: http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/3011077.3011111, doi:10.1145/3011077.3011111.
[31] Yu, D., Deng, L., 2016. Automatic Speech Recognition. Springer.
[32] Zribi, I., Kammoun, I., Ellouze, M., Belguith, L., Blache, P., 2016. Sentence boundary detection for transcribed tunisian arabic, in: 13th
Conference on Natural Language Processing (KONVENS 2016), pp. 323–331.

